<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epitaph, on the death of the late most reuerend Father in God, Iohn: by his prouidence the Arch-Byshop of Canterburie his Grace. &amp;c. Made to runne vpon the letters of his names and tytles. &amp;c. His Grace deceased at Lambeth in the yeere of his age 72. Februarie 29. 1603. And his funerall rightes were kept at Croyden the 27. of March following. 1604.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10291</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S115530</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850749</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850749</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15975</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10291)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15975)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1002:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epitaph, on the death of the late most reuerend Father in God, Iohn: by his prouidence the Arch-Byshop of Canterburie his Grace. &amp;c. Made to runne vpon the letters of his names and tytles. &amp;c. His Grace deceased at Lambeth in the yeere of his age 72. Februarie 29. 1603. And his funerall rightes were kept at Croyden the 27. of March following. 1604.</title>
                  <author>Rhodes, John, minister of Enborne, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W. White, dwelling in Cow-lane neere Smith-fielde,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: I.R., i.e. John Rhodes?--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>John .. Arch-byshop of Canterburie = John Whitgift.</note>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Whitgift, John, 1530?-1604 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:15975:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>IOHANNES WHITGIFTVS ARCHEP' Whitgiftus ruptris vinclis Romana relinquens Sacra pius, ſeſe meliores vertit ad vſus</p>
                  <figDesc>portrait of Archbishop John Whitgift</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15975:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>AN</hi> EPITAPH, On the Death of the late moſt reuerend Father in God, IOHN: by his prouidence the Arch-Byſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his Grace. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Made to runne vpon the letters of his Names and Tytles. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>His Grace deceaſed at <hi>Lambeth</hi> in the yeere of his age <hi>72.</hi> Februarie
<hi>29.</hi> 1603. And his Funerall rightes were kept at <hi>Croy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> the <hi>27.</hi> of March fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing. <hi>1604.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>The dayes of man are as Graſse: as a Flowre of the fielde, ſo flouriſheth hee. For the Winde goeth ouer it, and it is gone, and the place thereof ſhall know it no more.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103.15, 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London by W. White. dwelling in Cow-lane neere Smith-fielde. 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15975:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST REVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REND FATHER IN GOD, <hi>RICHARD,</hi> by Gods prouidence Byſhoppe of London. &amp;c.</head>
            <head type="sub">To the right Worſhipfull <hi>M. George Whitegift,</hi> and to all the kindred and friends of that name: <hi>I. R.</hi> wiſheth all health and comfort ouer their great heauineſſe, for the death of the late Arch-Byſhoppe of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his Grace. &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot to be tedious to your good Lordſhip, and Worſhips (conſidering your waigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie affaires at this time) In few wordes (preſuming vpon your courtecies) I preſent you with this poore <hi>Pamphlet</hi> or <hi>Epitaph,</hi> which I haue made on the death of the late moſt reuerend the <hi>Lord</hi> of <hi>Canterburie</hi> his Grace: (to whom I was much bounden and beholding, as many of his Gentlemen and others do well know.) And now being driuen with the ſtreame of my loue, duetie, and good-will to his grace, as alſo to your good L. and Worſhips: I can not but doe ſome thing (with others) as the laſt part of ſeruice that I can doe for his Grace in this life: I moſt humbly beſeech you all there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to accept well of the ſame, and to protect it vnder the winges of your fauours; and then I ſhall not need to care for <hi>Zoylus, Momas,</hi> and the reſt of that viperous brood. &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip, and Worſhips moſt humbly to be commaunded. <hi>I. R.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="acrostic" type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:15975:2"/>
            <head>A Flovver for the day.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> I See that <hi>Death</hi> dares ſeaze on Po-ten-tates,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> On Kinges, on Byſhop, and on all eſtates:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>H</label> How ſhall we maruell then, that this graue man,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>N</label> Now on the ſuddaine is thus dead and gon?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> was his Chriſten name, moſt men do know,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> ſignifies Gods <hi>grace, mercie,</hi> and ſo:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> was the firſt Fore-runner vnto Chriſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> an Apoſtle was to the moſt High'ſt:</l>
               <l>Some way we might report thus of his Grace,</l>
               <l>Who preacht and rulde, as beſt became his place.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>W</label> Well then, we ſee what our great ſinnes haue done,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>H</label> How God ſtill frownes on euery mothers ſonne,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> In taking Queene, and ſending Plagues withall:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>T</label> Thouſands did die, which bred our griefe and thall:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Enforſt with griefe, for this mans death, I ſay,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>G</label> God helpe the <hi>Clergie;</hi> for whoſe good I pray:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> If many ſuch ſhould die, where ſhould we finde,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>F</label> For his poore Church, a man ſo well inclinde:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>T</label> To ſpeake the trueth, hardly comes ſuch in place,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E,</hi> Except Gods ayde; therefore hard is their caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>White-gift</hi> our <hi>Delium</hi> Pearle, or Sun-ſhine bright,</l>
               <l>Virgin-like Piller, and Starre ſhining light:</l>
               <l>Is now Interred, and his ſoule at reſt</l>
               <l>Among the Sainctes, that are already bleſt:</l>
               <l>There to expect the Reſurrection day,</l>
               <l>When all th'elect ſhall liue with God for aye.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:15975:3"/>
               <l>
                  <label>T</label> The toyle he tooke, in Church &amp; Common wealth</l>
               <l>
                  <label>H</label> Haſt-ned his death, and did impaire his health:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Euen ſo it doth all great men in the Land.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet this all perſons will not vnderſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>A</label> Ah woe is vs, for thee; who can but moane,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Repent thy loſſe and lacke, now thou art gone:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>C</label> Come mournefull <hi>Muſes,</hi> and M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſirious eke,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>H</label> Helpe with your r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nes, Set <hi>dryrie doulfull</hi> lyke:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>B</label> Bring vs your Shackbuts that will rent the ground,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>Y</label> Your Citters &amp; Bandoras, with their ſiluer ſound:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>S</label> Sweete voyced <hi>Cliopae</hi> ſing to our Vearſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>H</label> Helpe vs this day about his Sable <hi>Hearſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> O <hi>England,</hi> let thy plaintes likewiſe appeare,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>P</label> Powre out thy ſobs for this our friend moſt deare:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Ecchous reſounding voyce in thee let ring,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For th' Arch-byſhops death, which is our hartes deepe ſting.</l>
               <l>Arch-Byſhop <hi>Yorke,</hi> and Byſhops of each See:</l>
               <l>Arch-Deacons, Deanes, and Prebends in degree:</l>
               <l>Churches Cathedrall Quires of Boyes and Men,</l>
               <l>Keepe you this Funerall both with tongue and pen.</l>
               <l>Organiſtes all, on ſoft ſtops giue the Kay,</l>
               <l>And let Subchaunter keepe good time all way:</l>
               <l>Maiſters of Children, Vergers all attende,</l>
               <l>Keepe a <hi>Decoram</hi> till the Herralds ende.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> Oh that our heades had <hi>Hieremy</hi> his teares,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>F</label> Fountaines might then flow many months &amp; yeares</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>C</label> Crying for him that quaild Church Robbers ſtill,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>A</label> And did defeate <hi>Dioniz'ous</hi> of his will.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N Nabals</hi> &amp; <hi>Newtors,</hi> they the Church would nurſſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T Thewdas</hi> and <hi>Iudas</hi> they would beare the Purſſe:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15975:3"/>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Euen as the Sea that eates into the land,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Right ſo did theſe; whom <hi>White-gift</hi> did withſtand.</l>
               <l>
                  <label>B</label> Bleſſed <hi>King Iames,</hi> helpe now in this, and flouriſh,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Elſe Learning, which doth true Relig'on nouriſh;</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Reuolters will deſtroy, and thee withall:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>Y</label> Yea, bring in Barbariſme, if we fall.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Come <hi>Canterbery,</hi> lat vs weepe with thee,</l>
               <l>For thou ſhalt miſſe <hi>White-gift,</hi> as well as wee.</l>
               <l>Clad all our Quire and Church with blacke throughout,</l>
               <l>Let Cittie, Walles, and Streetes be hung about:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Kent</hi> with her wealth, can not giue Blackes to all,</l>
               <l>That would be Mourners at this <hi>Fu-ne-rall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>H</label> Heare mee: his Grace wrongd no man with good will,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> In all his wayes he ſhund the Pathes of ill:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>S</label> Such as diſturbd the Church, he did aſſay,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>G</label> Godly to win, and leade an other way.</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Reu'rent he was, milde, gentle, and diſcreete,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>A</label> Affable, wiſe and ſober, as was meete:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>C</label> Certaine it is, mine eares did heare it plaine,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E, Enuie,</hi> that would him dead, wiſht him againe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His Grace was gratious vnto euery one,</l>
               <l>Eſpecially to Miniſters, when they made moane,</l>
               <l>His Grace won grace with men of each degree,</l>
               <l>In Court and Country, all the world did ſee.</l>
               <l>Graceleſſe are they, that will my wordes controule,</l>
               <l>Garceleſſe of credite, body, life, and ſoule.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>M</label> More might be ſayd of him, if Time gaue leaue</l>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Each man to pleaſe, but Time doth me bereaue.</l>
               <l>
                  <label>T</label> The <hi>Vniuerſeties,</hi> can ſpeake of him,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R</label> Report his life, and how he hated ſinne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15975:4"/>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> Oh <hi>Cambridge</hi> thou, and Colledges in thee,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>P</label> Powre out your plaintes, &amp; ſing this ſong with mee:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> O Colle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ge faires, that men call <hi>Trin-ne-tie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <label>L</label> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thy loſſe, and lacke of ſuch an eie.</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d knowne, what paines of late he tooke,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>T</label> Touching the Cleargie, and Communion Booke:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>A</label> And how he ſhewd our King the ready way,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>N</label> Now to prouide for Church, and Schollers ſtay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>euerend Fathers, follow you this thing,</l>
               <l>GOD is with you, and ſo is <hi>IAMES</hi> our King:</l>
               <l>What though Lay-men would ſwallow you, and all,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtand you faſt, and then their prides will fall:</l>
               <l>Meete <hi>Metropol'tans</hi> you may grow in time,</l>
               <l>Still to keepe out the Wilde-Boore from this Vine:</l>
               <l>Foxes and all, you ſhall driue hence at laſt:</l>
               <l>Now is the time, there is no good time paſt.</l>
               <l>Intreate and ſue, that no Land goe Tyth free,</l>
               <l>And that Tyth Statutes may explayned bee:</l>
               <l>Seeke that the Cleargie be not wronged ſtill</l>
               <l>By euery vpſtart, that would haue his will.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> O carefull <hi>Croyden,</hi> now to thee I ſpeake,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>F</label> For thine and <hi>Lambeths</hi> loſſe, our harts will breake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>A</label> Ah! Who ſhall do as <hi>White-gift</hi> did for you?</l>
               <l>
                  <label>L</label> Lay vp and build Schoole and Alms houſes too?</l>
               <l>
                  <label>L</label> Lord I know none, ſuch Blacke Swans are too rare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>E</label> Each man is bent to Au, rice euery where,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>N</label> None but the Lord, can ſet ſuch men in place,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>G</label> Gladly to pitty the poore man and his caſe:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>L</label> Let <hi>White-giftes</hi> worke, that ſtands thus in the eye,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>O</label> On each Arch-Byſhop for like worke ſtill cry:</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15975:4"/>
               <l>
                  <label>N</label> No doubt but God will then bleſſe them the more,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>D.</hi> Dayly increaſe their Baſket and their ſtore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of all Arch-Byſhops that for Trueth yet ſtood,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>White-gift</hi> and <hi>Mathew Parker</hi> did moſt good:</l>
               <l>As of all <hi>England</hi> therefore they had charge,</l>
               <l>So in all <hi>England</hi> they did good at large.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>England</hi> hath great cauſe both to laugh and weepe,</l>
               <l>Laugh for our King, and Triumphes that we keepe:</l>
               <l>Wayle for our ſinnes in Court and Country too,</l>
               <l>Moorne for this Man, and walke as moorners doe.</l>
               <l>See how this yeeres minde of late Q. comes in,</l>
               <l>Th' Aarch-Byſhops Fun'rall doth the ſame begin:</l>
               <l>God graunt we haue no moe ſuch doulefull yeeres,</l>
               <l>That ſhould thus threaten death of Prince or Peeres.</l>
               <l>No <hi>Engliſh</hi> Chronicle doth make relation,</l>
               <l>Of ſuch euentes, beyond all exſpectation.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>F</label> Feare God therefore, and do well to thy powre,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> In euery thing prepare for dying howre:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>N</label> Neuer preſume vpon thy ſtrength or youth:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>I</label> In any wiſe depende on God and Trueth:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S.</hi> So ſhalt thou come to heauenly ioyes at laſt,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>I.</label> Ioyfully leauing life, and pleaſures paſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>R.</label> Reſt ſo, and pray for King and Kingdomes all:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>C.</label> Chriſt then will bleſſe, &amp; keepe thee ſtill from thrall</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <label>Finis</label> this world, and worldly thinges we know,</l>
               <l>
                  <label>Finis</label> therefore our liues, when we muſt goe:</l>
               <l>
                  <label>Finis</label> the teares that doth run downe mens eyes,</l>
               <l>For <hi>White-giftes</hi> death, ſith they can not ſuffize.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Finis</hi> this Worke, and <hi>Epitaph</hi> of mine,</l>
               <l>Which to mens Charities I now reſigne.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:15975:5"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Finis</hi> in him, that <hi>Finis</hi> once ſhall make</l>
               <l>Of Sinne and Death, for all his choſen ſake:</l>
               <l>Infinite then, ſhalbe the mirth and ioy,</l>
               <l>That we ſhall haue with him in that great day.</l>
               <l>Vnto which ioyes, ſoone bring vs all O Lord,</l>
               <l>And keepe vs alwayes, ſteadfaſt in thy Word.</l>
               <l>In euery thing, looke well vnto the ende,</l>
               <l>Remember <hi>Death,</hi> and feare ſtill to offende:</l>
               <l>Count all thinges vaine, vnto Eter-ne-tie,</l>
               <l>Liue well, and thou ſhalt liue Eternalie.</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Short life by breath, the Learned ſtill do ſay,</l>
                  <l>Long life by Death, if we go the right way.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15975:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
